<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./lexicon.xsl" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="ta">iravam</title>
        <editor>
            <forename>Eva</forename> 
            <surname>Wilden</surname>
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Tamilex project.</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change/></revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <entry corresp="iravam[TL]">
        <form xml:lang="ta">iravam</form>
        <gramGrp><gram>noun</gram></gramGrp>
        <sense><def xml:lang="en"><abbr ref="#io"/>: turmeric</def>
<usg xml:lang="en">
</usg>
<cit source="https://uhh-tamilex.github.io/Purananuru/PN281.xml?id=PN281&amp;w=0,5">
    <q xml:lang="ta"><w>tīm</w> <w>kaṉi</w> <w><c type="glide">y</c>iravamoṭu</w> <w>vēmpu</w> <w>maṉai<c type="geminated">c</c></w> <w>cerīi</w></q>
    <q xml:lang="en">inserting in the house [the leaves of] Neem wood along with sweet-fruited tree-turmeric</q>
            <ref target="https://uhh-tamilex.github.io/Purananuru/PN281.xml?highlight=%5Bid%3DPN281%5D%20.l%3Anth-of-type(1)"><expan ref="#PN"/> 281, line 1</ref>
</cit>
<note xml:lang="en">
For this word isolated in the early corpus the <abbr ref="#TL"/> makes a separate entry, based on this passage, and a cross-reference to <foreign xml:lang="ta">iruḷmaram</foreign> [sic, without sandhi], “Ironwood of Ceylon (Mesua ferrea)”, without reference. Until actual occurrences of either word can be found, the likely explanation appears to be an etymological interpretation, reading <foreign xml:lang="ta">iruḷ</foreign>, “darkness” as equivalent to <foreign xml:lang="ta">iravam</foreign>, parallel form to the more frequent iravu or <foreign xml:lang="ta">irā</foreign>, “night”.</note>
<note xml:lang="en">The <abbr ref="#VAMTIPA"/> gives yet another gloss for the same <abbr ref="#PN"/> passage, <foreign xml:lang="ta">iravan taḻai</foreign>, "the foliage of <foreign xml:lang="ta">iravam </foreign>", refraining from an identification of the tree, probably based on the gloss given in the first complete <foreign xml:lang="ta">Puṟam</foreign> commentary by Tuṛaicāmip Piḷḷai: <foreign xml:lang="ta">iravamarattiṉ taḻai</foreign>.
 </note>
<note xml:lang="en">A more promising suggestion may be made, also on the basis of etymology, namely turmeric (<foreign xml:lang="la">Curcuma longa</foreign>). The <abbr ref="#TL"/> has a sub-entry under <foreign xml:lang="ta">iravu</foreign> with that meaning, evoking, as a possible explanation, Skt. <foreign xml:lang="sa">niśā</foreign>, “night”, also with a secondary meaning of “turmeric”. The combination of turmeric and neem is used until today in Ayurvedic medicine as an anti-infectant. If this is accepted, the <expan ref="#PN"/> would be the first place where these two plants are mentioned together. </note>
<note xml:lang="en">Another puzzle which has to be solved in this context is the attribute <foreign xml:lang="ta">tīm kaṉi</foreign>, with “sweet fruits”. This definitely does not make sense with the <abb ref="#TL"/> meaning of ironwood. This could in theory refer to quite a number of trees, but in Caṅkam literature the most likely candidate is <foreign xml:lang="ta">kāyā</foreign> (Memecylon edule), not a tree known for its fruit but for its dark blue flower. Sweet fruit is not very likely in connection with turmeric either, but it would work likely with a plant related in name though not in family, the tree turmeric (<foreign xml:lang="la">Berberis aristata</foreign>), which produces pretty red berries and can be used as an analgesic. Alternatively <foreign xml:lang="ta">tīm kaṉi</foreign> can be read in a figurative sense as referring to the good result to be expected from either <foreign xml:lang="ta">iravam</foreign> alone or it combination with <foreign xml:lang="ta">vēmpu</foreign>.
</note>
<note xml:lang="en">Note that neither the <expan ref="#Tiv"/> nor the <expan ref="#Pink"/> add <foreign xml:lang="ta">iravam</foreign> under the words for <foreign xml:lang="ta">mañcaḷ</foreign> (turmeric).
 </note></sense>
      <entry><gramGrp><gram>sociative</gram><gram>noun</gram></gramGrp><form xml:lang="ta">iravamoṭu</form></entry><cit type="lexicon"><bibl><date>1924–1936</date><title xml:lang="en">Tamil Lexicon (University of Madras)</title><ref target="https://dsal.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/app/tamil-lex_query.py?page=315">p. 315</ref></bibl></cit></entry>
      <listBibl>
      </listBibl>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>